Guide to the L. Frank Baum Collection
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
L. Frank Baum collection
1883-1982
YCAL MSS 13
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
2
(2 boxes)
The papers contain writings, production reviews, programs and advertisements, plus correspondence and other papers concerned with the collecting, publishing, and producing of Baum and his works.
Baum, L. Frank (Lyman Frank), 1856-1919
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Gift of Charles Beecher Hogan in 1968, 1977, 1979, and 1982.
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research.
LYMAN FRANK BAUM (1856-1919)
Lyman Frank Baum, author and playwright known for his children's books about the "Land of Oz," was born in 1856. His early career was in publishing, reporting, and editing for the Rose Lawn Home Journal (Syracuse, N. Y.), the World (New York City), and the Pioneer (Aberdeen, S. D.). In 1897 he established the Show Window, a periodical for window trimmers, and served as its editor until 1902.
In the meantime he dabbled in poetry and prose. His first dramatic work was The Maid of Arran, produced successfully in 1881 in New York City. His first popular book, written in 1899, was Father Goose: His Book. The Wonderful Wizard of Oz was published in 1900 and produced on stage in 1901; altogether Baum wrote fourteen "Oz" books.
He published many other books as well, under such pseudonyms as Floyd Akers, Laura Bancroft, John Estes Cooke, Capt. Hugh Fitzgerald, Suzanne Metcalf, Schuyler Staunton, and Edith Van Dyne.
Baum married Maud Gage in 1882 and had four children, Frank Joslyn, Robert Stanton, Harry Neal, and Kenneth Gage. He died at his home in Hollywood, California on May 6, 1919.
See: The National Cyclopaedia of American Biography, Vol. XVIII, pp. 331-2, for a list of Baum's books. See also: The Dictionary of American Biography, Vol. I., pp. 59-60.
Scope and Contents
The L. Frank Baum Collection contains some of Lyman Frank Baum's writings, production reviews, programs and advertisements, plus correspondence and other papers related to the collecting, publishing, and producing of his works. The material spans the dates 1883-1982.
The collection consists of twenty-nine folders in two boxes. Baum's writings (the first thirteen folders ) are arranged alphabetically and filed with material associated with the production of his works. Folder three contains a typed carbon copy of The Maid of Arran, folder six a fragment of the manuscript for The Tin Woodman of Oz, and folder thirteen a photocopy of the typescript for The Woggle-Bug Book. The items associated with the production of these and other works by Baum include newspaper and magazine reviews, theater programs, advertisements, and a few song book covers. Many of these items are copies (from negative microfilm) of material that was previously removed from a scrapbook. The remaining folders contain alphabetically arranged correspondence, some International Wizard of Oz Club material, and other papers relating to book collecting. Box two contains oversized items.
Most of the letters are addressed to Hogan but other recipients include fellow Baumanians, Jacob Blanck, Stewart Robb, and Mrs. Robert Ford. It was from Mrs. Ford that Hogan purchased The Tin Woodman of Oz manuscript on August 31, 1961.
There is one letter by Baum, an undated reproduction, that discusses the unknown recipient's writings, and a microfilm copy of a greeting card to his grandson. The more illuminating letters from Baum's wife Maud and his sons Frank and Robert contain anecdotes from Baum's life and information about the production of Baum's books on stage or in film.
The other letters give information about Baum's use of pseudonyms, variations in Baum's book titles and covers, and general bibliographic data.
The International Wizard of Oz Club material provides a glimpse into the mass-appeal of Baum's stories. The collection concludes with some book lists with prices. Oversize material, primarily advertisements and reviews associated with Baum's writings, is located at the end of the collection.
Charles Beecher Hogan's large L. Frank Baum collection is cataloged as printed material for The Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library and includes books, articles, scrapbooks, and illustrated games.
Authors, American; Children's literature, American; Collectors and collecting; Authors; Book collectors -- United States; Baum, L. Frank (Lyman Frank), 1856-1919; Hogan, Charles Beecher, 1906-; Baum family
- Writings, undated
  - The Magic Cloak of Oz: advertise- ment and program synopsis (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - The Maid of Arran: advertisement and program [copies from negative microfilm], 1883, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - The Maid of Arran [carbon typescript], 1885 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Matches: advertisement [copy from negative microfilm], n.d. (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Patchwork Girl of Oz: advertise- ment and review in The Moving Picture World [copy from negative microfilm], 1914 Oct 3, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - The Tin Woodman of Oz, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - The Tik Tok Man of Oz: reviews and song book cover [copies from negative microfilm], 1913 May 25, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 7)
    Related Archival Materials note
    See also: Box 2, folder 25
  - The Wizard of Oz: advertisements, reviews, and programs, 1902-64, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 8-12)
    See also: Box 2, folder 26
  - The Woggle-Bug Book [photocopy typescript], 1905 (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - The Woggle-Bug Book: advertisements and reviews, 1905, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 14)
    See also: Box 2, folder 27
- Correspondence, 1955 Jun 6
  - Baughman, Roland, 1955 Jun 6 (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - Baum, Frank J. (son), 1955 Dec 6 (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - Baum, L. Frank, 1909 Jul 14, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - Baum, Maud G., 1939 (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - Baum, Robert S., 1955 Nov 26 (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - Blanck, Jacob, 1942-3 (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - Kohn, John S. Van E., 1938 Feb 25 (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - Martin, Dick, 1960 (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - The Reilly & Lee Co., 1942 Jul 7 (Box 1, Folder 19)
  - Stark, Lewis M., 1955 Apr 6 (Box 1, Folder 19)
- The International Wizard of Oz Club, 1982, n.d.
  - Annual convention schedules, 1982, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 20)
  - Greene, Douglas and David: Oz puzzle (Box 1, Folder 20)
  - Hogan, C. Beecher: Membership card, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 20)
  - Schiller, Justin G., 1958 Oct 2 (Box 1, Folder 20)
- Other papers, n.d.
  - "L. Frank Baum is 'Broke', He Says": newspaper article [copy from negative microfilm], rough draft for cover to "Famous Tales and Laughter Stories," a title containing a contribution by Baum, and some book lists with prices (Box 1, Folder 21)
  - "The High-Jinks of L.F. Baum", 1959 (Box 1, Folder 22)
  - "Wizzing Down the Yellow Brick Road": West Coast Review of Books, 1976 Aug (Box 1, Folder 22)
  - The Wonderful World of Oz: The Works of L. Frank Baum, His Successors and Illustrators, 1983 (Box 1, Folder 23)
- Oversize, 1905
  - Jack Burgitt's Honor [photocopy], 1905 (Box 2, Folder 24)
  - The Tik Tok Man: reviews [copies from negative microfilm], 1913 (Box 2, Folder 25)
  - The Wizard of Oz: advertisements and reviews [originals and copies from negative microfilm], 1905-39, n.d. (Box 2, Folder 26)
  - The Woggle-Bug Book: advertisements and reviews [originals and copies from negative microfilm], 1905, 1924 (Box 2, Folder 27)
  - Book covers and publishers' advertisements [copies from negative microfilm], 1886, n.d. (Box 2, Folder 28)